同学们好，我是Yan，今天我们要谈论的是
hello students I'm Yan and today we're talking about
函数和栈帧
functions and frames
作为
as part
我们Pwn学院逆向工程模块的一部分
of our reverse engineering module of Pwn College
让我们开始吧
let's roll
简单的讲
on a high level
什么是程序
what is a program
程序是模块库、
a program is a collection of modules libraries
主二进制或者叫main
the main binary or the main
代码 的集合
code whatever
他们都由函数组成
that are each made up of a number of functions
这些函数包含
these functions contain
指令块
blocks collections of instructions
这些指令会操作数据结构中的变量
that operate on variables in data structures
然后触发系统调用
and then trigger system calls and do
并做你的程序要做的操作
whatever it is that your program is supposed to do
来启用该功能
to enable the functionality
没听清
you know and love
我们今天要讲的重点是
so the big thing here that we'll be talking about today
函数和它们由什么组成
is functions and what they're made up of
模块
of course modules you know
它们基本是装在
they are basic collections of functions shipped in
假设是一个库里的函数集合
let's say one library
它们被频繁调用
and they're very frequently used
来
to
让开发人员的工作更轻松
make developers lives easier
当你想编写
when you want to write
动态内存分配的时候
dynamic memory allocation
你不需要从头开始写
you don't have to write it from scratch
你可以使用libc库
you can use lib C
就是malloc free之类的
and its you know malloc free and so forth
这样的好处，也是我讲它的原因是
the nice thing and the reason I'm talking about this
它让逆向
here is that this makes it
更容易
much easier to reverse
通常情况下，除非你的逆向目标是
typically unless your reversing target is a
库本身，否则你不需要
library itself you don't have to
逆向库的代码
reverse engineer library code
库有良好的文档记录
libraries are well documented
你可以查阅他们的文档来理解
you can look up their documentation and understand
这个程序
what a program
嗯
that is
想要使用这个库实现什么功能
using a library is trying to achieve with this library
所以
right so
我们通常需要逆向的是
what we do have to reverse engineer often is
程序的主要模块
the main module of the program
好吧
all right
我们讲过
so we talked about
模块中有函数
the modules that you know include these functions
（语气词）
well
函数本身或多或少是一个功能单元
the functions themselves are more or less an atomic
嗯
um
一个功能单元
an atomic
我要说啥来着
my mind just went blank
原子，我要用的术语是什么来着
an atomic what's the term I'm looking for
我忘了
I don't know
模块（口误）是用于逆向的基础结构
the modules are an atomic construct for reversing
额，函数是逆向的原子结构
um the functions are atomic construct for reverse engineering
谢谢你对我的包容
thank you for bearing with me
一个函数通常有一个明确的目标
um a function has a well defined goal usually right
它实现了
has some functionality
一些功能
that it was written to implement
比如在面向对象编程中可能存在的
uh you might have a getter or setter function
getter或setter函数
object oriented programming
你的函数可以计算一些东西
your function might calculate something
也可能是个调度器，它
might dispatch other functions if it
解析用户、脚本或其他东西的输入，然后将数据传给其它函数
parses input from a user or from a script or something
这通常
and this typically
让他们
makes them
很适合单独进行逆向
well suited for being reversed engineered in isolation
通常你可以打开一个函数
typically you can open up a function
理解它的作用
understand what it does
其它逆向过的函数也会帮助理解
and having reversed other functions will help
当然，但是你知道存在
of course but there are you know
可以找到
you will be able to find functions
不需借助其它函数来理解的函数
that make sense on their own
当你逆向
and as you reverse engineer
越来越多的独立函数
more and more of these individual functions
你会开始
you'll start to
更好地理解
better understand
它们是如何组合在一起的
how they fit together
这种理解会在你的脑海中浮现
this understanding will emerge in your mind and
最终你会完全理解
eventually you will understand
你正在逆向的软件
the software that you're reverse engineering
函数是什么?函数是由图组成的
what is a function a function is made up of a graph
当然实际上
I mean of course you know that in
在elf文件中函数是由指令组成的
an elf file function is made up of instructions
但是从概念上讲
but conceptually speaking
总是一起执行的指令可以
these instructions can be
组成块
grouped into blocks that always execute together
并且连接这些块的边
and edges that connect these blocks
基于条件判断
based on conditional
控制着程序执行流程
unconditional control flow transfers
所以
and a
一个函数可以看作是一个图
the resulting function can be viewed as a graph
每次执行这个函数
every execution of this function
从概念上讲，就是穿过这个图的一条路径
conceptually speaking is a path through this graph
对吧
right
我们来看看
so let's look at
幻灯片的右边
the right side of these slides for
一个
a
我实现了一个很简单的
I I I implemented a very simple
cat
version of cat
它所做的就是等待，接受输入
right so all it does is it sits and takes input and
然后打印出来
and and spits it back out at you
这很简单
and it's very simple
实际上我是用汇编写的
I wrote it in assembly actually
而且是写完编译直接能运行
first shot it compiled and worked
我为自己感到非常自豪
I was very proud of myself
它有
and there's
2个函数，一个是elf可执行文件的入口点
2 functions basic there's the entry point of the Elf
_start
underscore start
它所做的就是调用main，然后
and all it does is call main and then it
调用退出
calls exit
好吧
right
然后是main函数
and then there's the main function
我们先暂时忽略开头
and let's ignore the beginning
这里，开始的地方
here where you know it starts
然后是这里，它退出的地方
and then the end where it returns for now
我们待会会深入研究的
we'll dig into that more
先看看这里的主体部分
and just look at kind of the main body here
从箭头可以看出
here we see just from the arrows
我们可以看到有一个循环
we can see that there's a loop
函数有一个while或for循环
that the function has a while or for loop
对，这说得通
right and this makes sense
Cat一直在等待，只要有输入
cat sits there and as long as there is input it
就产生输出
still produces output
然后你可以看到
and then you can see that
这条线是蓝色的
this this line is blue
这通常意味着它是无条件跳转
that typically means it's an unconditional jump
这个跳转总是会被执行
that will always be taken
这条线是绿色的
this line is green
这意味着只有在
this means this jump will only be taken if the
条件转移（口误）
conditional jump
与条件跳转相关的条件
the condition
的值为true的时候会跳转
associated with the conditional jump is true
这个跳转只会
and this jump will only be taken
在条件为假时发生
if the condition is false
所以你知道这个条件跳转不会被触发（因为触发了程序就退出了）
and so you know the conditional jump doesn't trigger
然后继续执行
and we just keep executing
我们来看看这是做什么的
so let's take a look at what this does
在这里你可以看到
right here you can see
如果你还记得
if you remember
shellcoding教学模块和沙箱教学模块（以后翻译）
from the shellcoding and sandboxing modules
非常熟悉的
very familiar setup of
read系统调用，Rax为0
the read system call Rax is 0
RDI为0，是从标准和输入读取
RDI is 0 is reading from standard and input
RSI指向栈
RSI is pointing at the stack
RDX设置为256
and RDX is set to 256
读取256
which reads 256
字节到栈
bytes onto the stack
然后拿返回值rax和
and then it checks it compares the return value R ax
和0比较，
against 0 and if
如果结果小于或等于0
the result is less than or equal to
如果你还记得汇编
if you recall from the Assembly
基础课程的话
Foundations lecture
这是一个条件跳转
this is a conditional jump
它检查
that checks
rax和和0之间的有符号比较
the assigned comparison between r ax and and the 0
最后的比较结果（在这里指rax与0的比较）
the last thing that was compared
如果是
and then if that is
小于0或小于等于0
less than zeros or less than equals 0
就是说如果read没有读到任何东西或者失败了
so if read didn't read anything or just failed
函数就返回
then the function returns
否则继续执行
otherwise it can execution continues
这里我们看到它设置了写系统调用
and here we see it sets up our write syscall
写出刚刚读到的内容到标准输出
writes out what it just read to standard output
然后再跳回来
and then jumps all the way back
所以你会发现
so you can see
只要顺着这张图
just by following this graph
理解这个图表的作用（口误）
and understanding what this graph does
理解这幅图的代表了什么
what this graph represents
我们刚刚逆向了
we just reverse engineered
我写的一个非常简单的程序
this very simple program that I wrote
当然在现实中
of course in reality
逆向的程序将会
the programs reverse engineer are going to be
明显增大
significantly larger
我们跳过了开头部分
so we skipped over the beginning in the end
函数
functions
当然有开始有结束，他们的
have a beginning an end of course and they have
开头叫序言，结尾叫尾声
in the beginning a prologue and then an epilogue
序言初始化了
the prologue sets up
函数的栈帧
what is called the stack frame for the function
尾声则把它拆掉
that epilogue tears it down
让我们先来探究一下这意味着什么
let's dig into what this means first
什么是栈
what is the stack
这是我们经常挂嘴边的
this is something we've casually tossed around
当我们在讨论汇编时
and we're talking about assembly
栈是一个内存区域，如果你还记得
well the stack is a memory region right if you recall
基础模块：
from the fundamentals Elf
什么是elf二进制文件
binary of what is an Elf
二进制文件基础课程
the Fundamentals Binary Files lecture
Elf有3个数据段，用于存储数据
an Elf has 3 data sections where it can store data
.data 用于预初始化
dot data is used for pre initialized
全局可写数据
global writable data
.rodata用于全局只读数据
dot rodata is used for global read only data
.BSS代表
the dot BSS stands for
额，sorry用于未初始化的全局可写数据
umm sorry is used for uninitialized global writable data
所以
right so
有很多地方可以存储全局数据
that's a lot of places to store global data
但是局部变量呢
but what about local variables right
很高兴你这么问
well I'm glad you asked
局部变量
local variables
活在栈上
live on the stack
栈用于存储局部变量
and the stack is used to store the local variables
还有函数的执行上下文
and also the execution context of the function
这个栈是由于历史上的一个奇怪现象
the stack due to a historical oddity
栈顶小地址，栈底大地址
grows backwards
出现这种情况是有原因的
there are reasons why this is the case
因为古代计算机的内存布局，但是
in terms of memory layouts on ancient computers but
我们留下了一个
really sickly we are left with a
有趣又有点奇怪的情况
interesting and kind of weird situation where
栈向后增长
the stack grows backwards
你可以
you can
垂直或水平绘制栈
draw the stack either vertically or horizontally
我喜欢水平画，因为
I like to draw it horizontally because it
这对我来说更容易理解
makes a lot of sense to me
这一堆从左边开始，然后
this stack starts on the left and then
或者更确切地说
or rather
这很有趣，因为我已经搞砸了
well this is funny because I already screwed up
当
this the when
内存地址向右递增
the order of increasing memories to the right
然而栈从右边开始
and then the stack starts on the right
我在视频中是镜像的，然后向左移动
I mirrored in the video and then goes to the left
原则是 当压栈时
the bottom line is when you push onto the stack
RSP降低8
RSP is decreased by 8
当出栈时RSP增加8
when you pop from the stack RSP is increased by 8
所以如果你看看当你压0x41
so if you look at what happens when you push OX41
然后压OX42，然后压OX43时会发生什么
then push OX42 then push OX43
我在这里画了对应的栈
I've drawn the stack here
水平和垂直的都画了
both horizontally and vertically
你可以
so you can get
理解它
familiar with it
大多数情况下我都用水平表示
I'll use the horizontal representation in most cases
因为
because it's
我们可以在一张幻灯片上放好几张
we can fit multiples of it on a slide and
然后看看栈是如何变化的等等
see how stacks change and so forth
好
alright
这就是栈
so that is um the stack
什么是栈的初始布局当
what's the initial layout of the stack when this
当程序开始时，额
when the program starts um
程序开始时
the program starts
栈保存了所有初始输入
the stack holds all of its kind of initial inputs
环境变量和参数
the environment variables and the argument um
这些值都指向参数值和um
both the the values pointers to the values and the um
参数数量
number of arguments
如果你看
so if you look at
这里的情况
this situation here
如果我有一个程序运行时带有参数hello world
if I have a program that I run with arguments hello world
和3个
and there are 3
环境变量， 那么在栈上
environment variables then on the stack
还有一些其他的东西
alongs with some other things that
我们现在不深入研究
that we won't dig into right now
有
there is
所有的字符串
all of the strings
以null结尾的字符串
null terminated strings one after the other
还有这些
and then there are these
它们被称为字符串表
string tables they're called
基本上是以空字节结尾的一系列指针
basically a series of pointers ending in a null byte
他们记录了环境变量和
and say this it holds for the environment and for
参数值
arguments argue V
你可以根据这些箭头看到它们的指向
and you can see they where they point to based on these arrows
当说argv[0]时，是指解引用
when you say argv[0] you are dereferencing
第一个参数，当你调用printf argv[0]时
the the first argument right when you do printf argue 0
它
it it
将
will
获取这个指针并将其传递给printf
take this pointer and pass it to a printf
这样就行了
which will do
你引用它，然后打印出字符串
you reference it and then print the string
当然还有argc
and then argc of course
参数的数量在栈的顶部
is the number of arguments at the top of the stack
好吧，接下来会发生什么
alright then what happens
然后当我们调用一个函数
then when we call a function
由于某些原因，这里有点问题，等一下让我来修正一下
and for some reason this is wrong one SEC let me fix it
好了
alright
我们回来了
we're back
不好意思，上面的橙色方块上没画
sorry this was missing on orange square on the top here
当我们调用main这样的函数时
when we call a function such as main
下一条指令的地址
the address of the next instruction
将压入栈
after the call is pushed to the stack
这条指令
so the instruction that
被调函数,main,返回时应该返回到这条指令
the callee that main should return to
所以如果你看
so if you look
call指令
the instruction that
的地址是401050
where call main is the address is 401050
下一条指令401055
the next instruction 401055
这就是将被压入栈的东西
and that is what will be pushed to the stack when
当我们调用Main时
we call Main
当main返回时，它就从栈上弹出了
okay and then when main returns it simply pops
从堆栈返回地址并跳转到那里
the return address from the stack and jumps there
就这么简单，这就是return
that's simple that is what a return is
你注意到
you notice that there are no
这段代码中没有Push和pop rip指令
push and pop rip instructions in this code
这些是隐式的压栈和弹栈
these are implicit pushes and pops
这就是call和jmp的区别
this is the difference between a call and a jump
call
a call
隐式地压栈
implicitly pushes something
return隐式地弹栈
return and implicitly pops it
而跳转实际上只是
whereas a jump actually just has a
跳到目标地址
target where you jump to
好
alright
我们继续
let's roll on
还有
there's also
栈上除了这些返回地址
aside from these return addresses on the stack
还有局部变量
there are local variables
这是函数存储局部变量的地方
this is where the function stores as local variables
在函数的开始
at the beginning of the function
它建立了
it sets up
用于存储局部变量的栈帧
a stack frame where it will store local variables
栈帧
the frame
是用两个东西建立的，栈指针
is built using 2 things the stack pointer
栈指针总是指向最左边(栈顶)
the stack pointer always points to the left most side
这里镜像了
I'm mirrored here
栈帧的最左边
the left most side of the stack frame
还有基指针
and the base pointer
总是指向最右边（栈底）
which always points to the right most side
这样做是为了
this is done so that
我们马上就会看到，清理时要容易得多
clean up is much easier as we'll see in a SEC
前言是
so the prologue is
我们将指向栈右边的旧帧指针压入栈
we push the old frame pointer what pointed to the old right side of the stack
如果Main
you know if Main
曾被
had been called by
另一个有帧指针的函数调用
another function that had a frame pointer
那样我们以后可以更容易地恢复它
so that we could restore it easier later
我们
and we
移动
move
当前在最左边的栈指针（rsp）
the current stack pointer the left most side
进入帧指针（rbp）//rsp赋值给rbp
into the frame pointer
现在最右端和最左端
so now the right most side and the left most side
指向相同的位置
are pointing to the same location
这是栈的顶部
this is the top of the stack
函数的开头
the beginning of this functions
栈帧
stack frame
返回地址就在栈帧的右边
with the return address directly to the right of it
接着我们减去
and then we subtract from
我们把rsp减去局部变量占用的大小（包含字节对齐等）
let me for you we subtract from the stack pointer
来在栈上分配空间
to create space on the stack now
我把讲的和幻灯片中的allocate加上了引号
I have allocate and the slides in quotes
这是因为实际上没有空间被创造出来
this is because no space actually created
里面的空间和数据一直都在
the space and the data in it was always there
我们只是从概念上讲
we just now kind of conceptually
做了个记号
marked it as you know
在这个函数栈栈帧中
within this functions stack frame
因为
because
栈指针指向栈帧的左边
the stack pointer is pointing to the left of it
还有帧指针（rbp）
and the frame pointer
基指针（rbp）指向它的右边
the base pointer is pointing to the right of it
好，然后执行函数体
cool and then the function executes
它可以随心所欲地使用栈
it uses its stack howver it wants
函数执行完后它把这个栈帧释放了
and then it tears down this frame
这是
and this is
也非常非常简单，因为有这些基指针（rbp）
also very very simple because of these base pointers
好，我们释放
right we deallocated
这里我也加了引号
and here again I have quotes
因为数据并没有消失
because the data is not gone
它非常快乐地呆在那里
it stays around perfectly happily
我们只是将栈指针（rsp）移到数据的右侧（+）
we just moved the stack pointer to the right of that data
所以这些数据并不
so that data is not really
在栈中了（在内存的栈空间，但没有函数使用）
kind of within the stack anymore
但它并没有被摧毁
but it's not destroyed
这是非常重要的一点
that's a very important thing
这实际上导致了很多漏洞
that leads to a lot of vulnerabilities actually
那个，数据
is that that data
还在那里，如果
stays around so if
首先，当栈帧被拆除时，数据还在
and first of all it stays around when the stack frame is torn down
而且当新栈帧建立时，它不会被任何东西覆盖
and it's not overridden with anything when the stack frame is set up
所以可以导致这样的情况
so you can lead to situations where
数据在不应该被重用时被重用，敏感数据可能被泄露
data is reused when it shouldn't be reused and sensitive data can be leaked
不管怎样
anyways
我们通过重置栈指针来释放栈
we deallocate the stack by by resetting the stack pointer
不好意思，栈指针在栈最左边
sorry the stack pointer which is on the left most side of the stack
把rbp赋值给rsp
2 point to to be equal to the frame pointer
栈帧指针和基指针等价
the base pointer that used interchangeably
这俩术语
that those terms
rbp在栈帧的右边
is on the right side of the stack frame
通过将RBP赋值给RSP
and by just moving RBP into RSP
我们从栈弹出旧的base指针（rbp）
we pop the old base pointer
这样我们就完全恢复了旧的栈帧
so that we restore fully the old frame
函数调用者的栈帧
of the function that called us
现在我们准备返回了
and now we are ready to return
现在栈上的下一个东西是返回值
now the next thing on the stack is the return value
所以当我们返回的时候（ret指令隐式的pop然后jmp）
so that when we ret it
它会正常工作的
it'll it'll work properly
最后一件事
one final thing
是 现在有的
is there are now
优化参数和现代编译器可以不使用
optimizations and modern compilers that can not use
可以把 RBP 当作
that can enable using RBP as
一个
a
通用寄存器而不是帧指针来使用
general purpose register instead of the frame pointer
所以不要惊慌
so don't panic
如果你看到没有把RBP压栈
if you see something that does not use RBP to set up the stack
就直接对RSP进行操作
that does operation directly on RSP
不把rbp赋值给rsp，直接把RSP增加100（拆除栈帧）
so instead of move RSP RBP it might add RSP 100
它可能仍会压高RBP，因为
it will likely still push RBP because
这是调用约定（计划不是）的一部分
that is part of the calling convention and in fact
你会经常看到有的序言会push其它寄存器
the prologue you'll often see pushing other registers
我们在基础汇编课的调用约定部分讨论过
which as we discussed in the calling convention part of the Fundamentals Assembly lecture
被调用者保存寄存器
are callee saved registers
在函数中覆盖它们而不恢复它们被认为是不礼貌和不恰当的
and that it is considered impolite and improper to overwrite them without restoring them within a function
这就是函数，从代码和数据角度来看
okay that is what a function is from both the code and the data perspective
而且
and
它是如何
how it
函数在执行过程的生命周期
the life cycle of a function as it lives in executes
接下来我们将讨论
and next we'll talk about
数据以及如何分辨不同种类数据的位置
the data and how to tell where different data is
下节课见
see you next video